[{"question":"<p><strong>Structural unemployment is mainly caused by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Seasonal variations","Changes in production techniques","Changes in the demand pattern of an economy","Shortage of information about job opportunities"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>The total money values of all goods and services produced in a country during a certain period is measured using the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Income method","Expenditure method","Output method","Factor method"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>The loans from the World Bank to developing countries are mainly to support<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The establishment of more universities","Capital intensive technology","Their low level of consumption","Infrastructural investments"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>Fiscal policy is the government&rsquo;s plan to control aggregate demand by manipulating<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Revenue and expenditure","The demand and supply of money","Tastes and preferences of consumers","The structure of production and employment"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>A commodity will be demanded only if<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Consumers income increases","It has no close substitutes","The price is low","It has utility"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>If P = &frac12; (Qs + 15). What is the quantity supplied at N9.00?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1.5","3.0","12.0","33.0"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>A public liability company is run on a daily basis by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The chief executive","The shareholders","The board of directors","Financial consultants"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>The term balance of trade can be defined as the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Relation between value of exports and value of imports over a given period of time","Balance owed to the rest of the world in payment for imports","Price paid for imports in terms of exports","Relation between payments of all kind made by a country to the rest of the world over a given period of time."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>The main function of price mechanism is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Limit consumer demand","Enable producers make profit","Allocate scarce resources among competing needs","Ensure consumer sovereignty"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>Average Fixed Cost is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Average Total Cost less the sum of Average Variable Cost","Half the sum of all costs","Total Fixed Cost divided by the level of output","Total Fixed Cost plus Marginal Cost"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a good is an inferior good, then<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It is also necessarily a Giffen good","The quantity of the good demanded varies inversely with its price","Its income elasticity of demand is negative","The poor buy the good only out of habit"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>The Law of Diminishing Returns begins to operate when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Total product begins to rise","Total product begins to fall","Marginal product begins to fall","Marginal product begins to rise"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the dangers of the localization of industries is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Residual unemployment","Mass unemployment","Cyclical unemployment","Structural unemployment"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a government wants to reduce the level of inflation, it will<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Run a budget surplus","Run a budget deficit","Run a balanced budget","Borrow more money"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>An issue of bank-notes not backed by gold but by government securities is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Fiduciary issue","Guaranteed money","Seigniorage","Legal tender"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2017"},{"question":"<p><strong>The effect of emigration on a country&rsquo;s population all other things remaining equal is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Increase its size","Cause overpopulation","Increase its growth rate","Reduce its size"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The elasticity of supply of perishable goods is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Elastic","Zero","Inelastic","Unitary"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>If the cost of production for a firm continues to increase as its output rises, the firm is said to be experiencing<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Large scale production","Profit maximization","Economies of scale","Dis-economies of scale"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The primary problem of economics is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["To obtain a more equitable distribution of money income","Production of a given output with the lowest cost combination of factors of production","Adoption of capital-intensive technology","Increasing the quantity of the fixed factor of production"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The basic principles of co-operative societies are those of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Active participation of capitalists in the affairs of co-operative societies","Workers ownership and worker control","Sole proprietorship","Partnership"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In estimating the national income of a country, the three approaches usually adopted are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Expenditure, value-added and output","Income, final product and output","Expenditure, income and output","Avoidance of double counting, final expenditure and value-added"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The natural growth rate of a population is the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Sum of the birth rate and the death rate","Sum of the birth rate and the net migration","Birth rate minus death rate","Birth rate divided by net migration"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Localization of industries refers to the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Tendency to concentrate industries in particular areas","Siting of industries in certain areas","Deliberate policy of influencing location of industries generally","Zoning of industries"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>GDP differs for GNP because GDP<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Is inclusive of depreciation","Emphasizes the final goods and services produced within the country at a particular period","Emphasizes the goods and services produced within the country","Emphasizes the market value of all final goods and services produced by nationals"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>At any given level of output, the total cost of a firm equals the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Marginal cost plus the average cost","Fixed cost less its variable cost","Average cost multiplied by its output","Economic costs multiplied by variable cost"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>If two commodities are good substitutes for one another, an increase in the demand for one will reduce the demand for the other. This type of demand is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Composite demand","Elastic demand","Competitive demand","Inelastic demand"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>As long as marginal utility is positive, the total utility must be<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Negative","Increasing","Zero","Decreasing"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Inductive method of scientific reasoning involves<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Drawing conclusions from specific to general","Making inferences based on theory","Using past to explain the present","Drawing conclusions from general to specific"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The ability of commercial banks to create money depends on the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Reserve ratio","Liquidity ratio","Interest rate","Capital base"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given that the total cost is 1000, total variable cost is 2500 and the output 100 units. The average cost of producing one unit is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["60","45","35","30"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>The table below gives the market demand schedule for commodity X<\/strong><br><strong>Price (N) Quantity (million units)<\/strong><br><strong>60&nbsp; &nbsp; 100<\/strong><br><strong>50&nbsp; &nbsp; 140<\/strong><br><strong>40&nbsp; &nbsp; 220<\/strong><br><strong>30&nbsp; &nbsp; 260<\/strong><br><strong>20&nbsp; &nbsp;300<\/strong><br><strong>10&nbsp; &nbsp;340<\/strong><br><strong>If the price of a commodity X falls from N40.00 to N30.00, what is the price elasticity of demand?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.62","0.73","1.00","1.50"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>In estimating the national income of a country, the three approaches usually adopted are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Expenditure, value-added and output","Income, final product and output","Expenditure, income and output","Avoidance of double counting, final expenditure and value-added"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>The value of the multiplier depends on<\/strong><\/p>","options":["MPC and a level of income","Level of personal income","Level of personal savings","Government policy and MPC"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Contractionary monetary policy is used to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Control inflation","Bridge the deflationary gap","Expand the output level","Deregulate the economy"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>At any given level of output, a firm&rsquo;s total variable cost equals<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Total cost less marginal cost","Total cost less total fixed cost","Total cost less average cost","Average variable cost and marginal variable cost"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the most important factors that should be considered in the location of an industry is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Nearness to the financial centre","Assured patronage by government functionaries","Availability of inputs and market","Availability of adequate security"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given that the total cost is 1000, total variable cost is 2500 and the output 100 units. The average cost of producing one unit is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["60","45","35","30"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>The value of the multiplier depends on<\/strong><\/p>","options":["MPC and a level of income","Level of personal income","Level of personal savings","Government policy and MPC"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>External diseconomies of scale results from excessive growth of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The whole industry","Some sectors of the industry","External factors","Internal factors"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>A country with over-valued currency will<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Expect balance of payments surplus","Have increased demand for her exports","Increase her foreign reserve","Decrease her foreign reserve"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the short run, a firm&rsquo;s marginal cost curve above the point of shut-down is its<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Demand curve","Supply curve","Revenue curve","Cost curve"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>In a planned economy, the emphasis is on<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Public ownership and control","Prices and competition","Individual choices and decisions","Private ownership and control"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>To compare the standard of living among nations, the most widely used economic indicator is the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Real domestic output","Real gross national income","Real per capital income","Per capital nominal income"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>When the importation of a commodity is limited to a definite quantity, the trade control means used is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Exchange control","Tax relief","Devaluation","Quotas"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>A firm operating at full capacity will experience rising short-run costs when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Prices of its variable inputs rise","Prices of its variable inputs fall","There is change in management","Labour productivity increases"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>The distinction between onshore and offshore operations lies in the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Location of sites","Output generated","Size of production","Techniques of production"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>The burden of a government tax on a commodity whose demand is inelastic will<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Be borne only by the government","Fall more heavily on consumers","Be shared equally between consumers and producers","Fall more heavily on producers"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>A major advantage of industrialization is that it<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Leads to self-reliance","Curbs inflation","Leads to growth and development","Improves the terms of trade"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>A firm operating at full capacity will have a<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Perfectly inelastic supply curve","Perfectly elastic supply curve","Fairly elastic supply curve","Fairly inelastic supply curve"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>The movement of people from rural to urban areas affects the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Occupational distribution of population","Sex distribution of population","Geographical distribution of population","Age distribution of population"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>The export-promotion strategy is aimed at producing<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Consumer goods originally imported","Machinery for industries","More goods for exports","More goods of domestic consumption"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"<p><strong>Suppose that the equilibrium price of an article is N500 but the government fixes the price by law at N400, the supply will be<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The same as the equilibrium supply","Greater than the equilibrium supply","Less than the equilibrium supply","Determined later by the government"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is not a direct tax?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Company income tax","Capital tax","Purchase tax","Personal Income Tax"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The process by which West African countries attempt to reduce the import of manufactured goods by encouraging firms to produce theses at home is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Industrialization","Export promotion","Import substitution","Export substitution"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The basic principles of co-operative societies are those of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Active participation of capitalists in the affairs of co-operative societies","Worker ownership and owner control","Sole proprietorship","Partnership"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Foreign exchange control in Nigeria is administered by the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["United Bank for Africa","Union Bank of Nigeria","First Bank of Nigeria","Central Bank of Nigeria"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The rate of exchange between a domestic and a foreign currency is defined as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Terms of trade","Domestic currency price of a unit of the foreign currency","Foreign currency price of gold","Domestic currency price of gold"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A perfect example of a public good is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Air","Education","Defense","Transport"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A school girl who needs a book and a mirror, each costing five naira decides to purchase the book instead of the mirror since she cannot pay for the two at the same time. Determine the real cost of her cost.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The five naira she spent on the book","Five naira real cash value","The mirror","The book"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A system in which the means of production is held in trust for the people by government is known as a<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Social economy","Capitalist economy","Subsistence economy","Mixed economy"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A firm determines its profits when it studies its<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Marginal cost","Average cost","Total cost","Average cost relative to price in the market"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given that the elasticity of demand for a commodity is 2.5, the percentage change in the quantity demanded as a result of 10% change in its price is?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.25","0.40","4.00","25.00"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the major consequences of urban-biased development programs in Nigeria is that they<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Led to rapid rural-urban migration","Led to unprecedented urban wealth","Transformed rural areas into urban centres","Increased the level of specialized manpower in the cities"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>An increase in discount rate is an indication of a central banks intention to pursue<\/strong><\/p>","options":["An expansionary monetary policy","A disciplined monetary policy","A dynamic monetary policy","A contractionary monetary policy"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the problems arising from the localization of industries is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["High prices of output","The exportation of output","The scarcity of foreign exchange","Structural unemployment"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>An important factor hindering the rapid development of the industrial sector in Nigeria is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Rural-urban migration","Excessive demand for finished products","Inadequate infrastructural facility","The dominance of the oil sector"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economic goods are termed scarce goods when they are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Not available in sufficient quantities to satisfy all wants for them","Not purchased in sufficient quantities to satisfy the effective demand for them","Of high quantity","Of primary importance in satisfying needs of a society"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The demand of a commodity is affected by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The consumer of the commodity","The price of the commodity alone","The price of the commodity, income of the consumer, prices of other commodities and preferences of the consumer","Government policy"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The demand curve can be derived from<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The total utility curve","The cardinal utility theory","The marginal curve","All of the above"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The basic idea behind the brand differentiation under the imperfect market arrangement is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Stimulate demand for rival product","Create demand for the particular product","Enable the product to penetrate the market","Enable the product to compete with other products"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Consumption plus investment plus government purchases plus net exports make up<\/strong><\/p>","options":["National income","Net national income","Net national product","National product"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The role of the central bank in the economic development of Nigeria is to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Use cheques and bank drafts to facilitate business transactions","Maintain a stable price system","Give short and medium term loans to the public","Give financial and technical advice to customers"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The average tax rate is defined as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Total tax rate less the marginal tax rate","The tax rate which applies to additional value of income","The ratio of the total taxes paid to total income","Marginal tax rate for being progressive"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is a good example of invisible item, on balance of payments account?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Shipping and aviation","Exports and imports","Merchandise","Bullion"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economic decisions are taken<\/strong><\/p>","options":["At the margin","At once as consumption goes on","At the beginning of events","At the level of the household"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>If units of a variable factor are increasingly added to a fixed factor and the marginal physical product keeps increasing, production is said to be taking place under conditions of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Increasing returns to the variable factor","Fixed cost less its variable cost","Constant returns to the variable factor","External economies of scale"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Short run period in production is a period too short for a firm to be able to change its<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Scale of production","Total revenue","Variable inputs","Total outputs"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A firm&rsquo;s shut-down point is reached when the average revenue fails to cover the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Marginal cost","Average fixed cost","Average total cost","Average variable cost"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The need to construct a scale of preference is necessitated by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The need to satisfy wants","Scarcity and the need for choice","Scarcity of resources","Non-availability of factors of production"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>If at 10k per kg, 1000kg of yam were purchased and at 5k per kg, 1500kg were purchased, the resultant point elasticity of demand is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.33","0.0001","1","10,000"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a wage increase is granted to a cement manufacturer&rsquo;s worker, the supply curve of cement will<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Move to the right","Move to the left","Move to the opposite side","Move to nowhere"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The elasticity of supply of perishable goods is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Inelastic","Elastic","Unitary","Zero"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The average product of labour in a given period is obtained by dividing the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Number of workers by the total product","Total product by the number of hours actually worked","Change in total product by the change in the total number of workers","Total product by the number of workers"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A possible factor which limits the extent of growth of a firm is the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Existence of a monopoly","Bureaucratic delays in decision making","Use of by-products","Unwillingness to share ownership and control"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A major difference between a state-owned enterprise and a private enterprise is that the former<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Is not expected to cover its cost of production while the latter is","Is not always expected to maximize profits while the latter is","Has shareholders while latter does not","Has a board of directors while the latter does not"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The main handicap of sole proprietorship is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Limited liability","Lack of technical know-how","Low profit margin","Inadequate capital"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Taxes and government expenditures are instruments of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Monetary policy","Tax policy","Economic policy","Fiscal policy"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>If C stands for consumption, I for investment, X for exports and M for imports, then national income is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["C + I + X + M","C + I + X \u2013 M","C + I \u2013 X + M","C + I + X"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A capital market differs from the money market in that in the former<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Loan sought is long-term","Loan repayment is guaranteed","Loan sought is short-termed","The percentage of interest charged is more"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The money market is a financial market that specializes in the provision of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Short-term loans and advances","Medium-term loans","Long-term loans","Venture capital for the development projects"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>There is an improvement in the terms of trade of a country if<\/strong><\/p>","options":["A large quantity of exports is given to obtain a unit of imports","The volume of exports is greater than the volume of imports","A small quantity of exports is given up to obtain a unit of imports","The value of exports is greater than the value of imports"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A country with over-valued currency will<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Decrease her foreign reserve","Have increased demand for her exports","Increase her foreign reserve","Expect balance of payments surplus"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>In an agricultural economy, a poor harvest which diverts demand away from industrial goods leads to trade cycle by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Leading to an increase in labour\/capital ratio","Leading to constant labour\/capital ratio","Leading to increased capital investment","Leading to an increase in capital\/output ratio"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The production possibility curve can be used to explain the underlying concepts of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Scale of preference and choice","Opportunity cost and choice","Wants and means","Opportunity cost and scale of preference"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>If the increase in the price of yam is used to estimate the inflation rate, this is an example of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Deductive reasoning","Inductive reasoning","Normative reasoning","Positive reasoning"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>54, 35, 62, 79, 83, 36, 62, 42, 62, 42. Calculate the mean<\/strong><\/p>","options":["45.5","55.7","55.8","65.8"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>54, 35, 62, 79, 83, 36, 62, 42, 62, 42<\/strong><br \/><strong>Calculate the modal score<\/strong><\/p>","options":["36","42","54","62"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>A major determinant of demand for a luxury good is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The price of the good","Price of other goods","The income of consumers","Taste and fashion"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>As long as marginal utility is positive, total utility must be<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Negative","Increasing","Zero","Decreasing"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the factors affecting the supply of manufactured good is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Weather","Technology","Consumer tastes","Availability of inputs"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>An upward movement along the same supply curve results in<\/strong><\/p>","options":["An increase in supply","A decrease in price","A decrease in quantity supplied","An increase in quantity supplied"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>An example of an indirect tax is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Profit tax","Sales tax","Capital gain tax","Poll tax"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>An example of an indirect tax is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Profit tax","Sales tax","Capital gain tax","Poll tax"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>A major consideration in locating a cement factory is the availability of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Skilled labour","Power","Infrastrutural facilities","Limestone"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The activities of the oil and gas industries are classified into<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Exploration and transportation","Upstream and downstream","Discovery and extraction","Onshore and offshore"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Joint-stock companies can raise funds from<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The money market","The capital market","Various sources","Government"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>To protect farmers during a bumper harvest, the government usually<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Sets a maximum price","Releases products from the buffer stock","Sells the excess to consumers","Sets a minimum price"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Contractionary monetary policy is used to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Control inflation","Bridge the deflationary gap","Expand the output level","Deregulate the economy"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The output approach to measuring national income is based on the computation of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Final output","Factor cost","Value added","Profits earned"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Developments outside a given firm which reduce the firm&rsquo;s costs are called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Internal economies","External economies","External diseconomies","Optimum effects"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>If X represents the factors of production and Y represents the price factor, which of the following sets of association is correct?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["(land, rent), (capital, wage), (labour, profit)","(land, interest), (capital, profit), (labour, wage)","(land, wage), (capital, interest), (land, rent)","(land, rent), (capital, interest), (labour, wages)"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>If at 10k per kg, 1000kg of yam were purchased and at 5k per kg, 1500kg were purchased, the resultant point elasticity of demand is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.33","0.0001","1","10,000"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>A situation in which all inputs are doubled and output also doubles is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Constant proportions","Constant returns","Increasing returns to scale","Constant returns to scale"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economic goods are termed scarce goods when they are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Not available in sufficient quantities to satisfy all wants for them","Not produced in sufficient quantities to satisfy the effective demand for them","Of high quality","Of primary importance in satisfying the needs of society"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following situations will give rise to economic problems?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["unlimited human wants","wants of varying importance","limited means for satisfying wants","means used in different ways"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Population <\/strong><br \/><strong>(Million) Food Prouduction<\/strong><br \/><strong>(Million tones)<\/strong><br \/><strong>50 220<\/strong><br \/><strong>70 210<\/strong><br \/><strong>90 225<\/strong><br \/><strong>100 275<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p><strong>In the table above, what is the optimum population in million?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["50","70","90","100"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>An accurate census is important to a country because it helps<\/strong><\/p>","options":["In solving unemployment problem","To ensure equitable population distribution relative to natural resources","In deciding on creation of more local government","In providing sound basis for formulating development policy"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Circular flow of income defines the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Relationship between end and means in the economic system","Allocation of income to various members of the household","Flow of goods, services and money amongst the various macro-section of the economy","Microeconomic relationships in economic analysis"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the long run, all production factors are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Fixed","Semi-fixed","Variable","Semi-variable"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>The advantages which firms obtain directly from expanding their operations are referred to as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Internal economies of scale","External economies of scale","Economies of localization","Economies of resources allocation"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>The effect of changes in the condition of demand on a demand schedule with the price constant is a<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Movement along the demand curve","Deflation of the demand curve","Hyperbola formation by the demand curve","Shift of the demand curve"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a demand curve that intersects a price inelastic supply curve shifts rightward,<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The equilibrium price and quantity increases","Only the price will increase","Only the quantity will increase","The price will remain constant"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>The average product of labour in a given period is obtained by dividing the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Number of workers by the total product","Total product by the number of hours actually worked","Change in total product by change in the total number of workers","Total product by the number of workers"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>If the cost of production for a firm continues to increase as its output rises, the firm is said to be experiencing<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Large scale production","Profit maximization","Economies of scale","Diseconomies of scale"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following best describes the production function?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It indicates the best output to produce","It relates naira inputs to naira outputs","It relates physical outputs to physical inputs","It indicates the best way to combine factors to produce any given output"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given perfect competition in the capital market, the opportunity cost of capital is adequately reflected by the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Interest rate","Returns on capital","Alternate capital forgone","Shadow price of foreign exchange"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following reward is associated with enterpreneurship as a factor of production?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Salaries","Profits","Interests","Rents"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>In a market economy, the question of what, how and for whom to produce are solved by the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Elected representative of the people","Planning committee","Price mechanism","Government"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>At any given level of output, a firms total variable cost equals<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Total cost less marginal cost","Total cost less total fixed cost","Total cost less average cost","Average variable cost and marginal variable cost"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>At any given level of output, a firms total variable cost equals<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Total cost less marginal cost","Total cost less total fixed cost","Total cost less average cost","Average variable cost and marginal variable cost"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Age groups (years) Distribution (%)<\/strong><br \/><strong>Above 60 30<\/strong><br \/><strong>15 &ndash; 60 45<\/strong><br \/><strong>0 - 14 25<\/strong><br \/><strong>The estimated dependency ratio of the population shown above is:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["11:9","9:11","7:3","3:7"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following factors is NOT responsible for the rural\/urban drift in Nigeria?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The infrastructural facilities in the cities","Declining fertility of rural farmlands","Rural electrification programme","Higher living standards in urban areas"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>The necessity of choice is due to the fact that<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Human wants are insatiable","Customers like to maximize satisfaction","Resources are abundant","Consumers are selective"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>What is meant by labour supply?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Number of people in working population","Number of men and hours they work","Number of hours during which the middle-aged persons work","Number of workforce multiplied by the hours they worked"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>The market where there are many differentiated products is called<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Monopoly","Perfect competition","Monopolistic competition","Oligopoly"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the dangers of localization of industries is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Residual unemployment","Mass unemployment","Structural unemployment","Cyclic unemployment"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>In commercial banking, an account from which a customer cannot withdrew money instantly is a<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Demand deposit account","Time deposit account","Special deposit account","Saving deposit account"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Banks can create more money by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Increasing their cash ratio with the central bank","Issuing more bank cheques","Accepting more deposits from customers","Lending out money from customers\u2019 deposits"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>The most important factor in ensuring economic development is the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Effective mobilization of domestic savings","Presence of foreign account","Formulation of appropriate government policies","Attraction of foreign aids and grants"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Scarcity in economics means that<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Human wants are limitless","The economy has very few resources","The economy can scarcely produce anything","Resources are limited"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Air is essential to life but commands no price! Diamond is not essential to life but commands a high price! This is the paradox of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Thrift","Value","Abundance","Scarcity"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economies of scale operate only when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Marginal cost is falling with input","Average cost is falling with input","Fixed cost is variable","Variable cost is less than fixed cost"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Efficiency in production involves<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Reducing the size of workforce","Producing a given output with the lowest cost combination of factors of production","Adoption of capital intensive technology","Increasing the quantity of the fixed factor of production"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>An effect of inflation is that it _ _ _?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Discourages trade by barter","Favours debtors at the expense of creditors","Increases the real income of salary earners","Increases the value of a country\u2019s exports"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>The migration of young people from rural areas in Nigeria should help to raise the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Standard of living in the urban areas","Total productivity of labour in the rural areas","Marginal productivity of labour in the rural areas","Marginal productivity of labour in the urban areas"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>A modern corporation is owned by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Debenture holders","Ordinary shareholders","Preference shareholders","Creditors"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of the most important factors that should be considered in the location of an industry is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Nearness to  the financial centre","Assured patronage by government","Availability of inputs and market","Availability of adequate security"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>What is the term used to describe a policy aimed at promoting the local production of goods which are usually imported?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Deregulation","Import substitution","Tariff reduction","Backward integration"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Progressive tax structure is designed to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Take more from the income of the poor","Take more from the income of the rich","Take equal proportion of income from both the rich and the poor","Reduce the problems emanating from tax imposition"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>The use of legally permissible means to reduce tax liabilities is known as tax<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Evasion","Avoidance","Relief","Exemtion"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>The greatest proportion of government revenue in Nigeria comes from<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Export of raw materials","Income taxes on individuals and businesses","Custom duties and excise taxes","Loans and grants from industrially advanced countries"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Privatization of government owned companies means the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Relinqishing of government\u2019s equity","Recapitalization of private individuals","Joint participation of government and private individuals","Commercialization and deregulation of the economy"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Gains from trade depend on<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Comparative advantage","Absolute advantage","Distributive cost advantage","Absolute cost advantage"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>A country&rsquo;s import price index by 1995 was 50 and her index of export price was 70, calculate the terms of trade<\/strong><\/p>","options":["20%","71%","120%","140%"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"}]